Zoe: So I think the key things I've
done to change my communication style
is using very literal language rather
than adding in any sarcasm or phrases
that wouldn't make sense literally.
Kerry: It's about all forms
of communication being valid.
So we've got pod books, we've got pecs
books, we've got other forms of AAC.
We're trialing iPods, which is like a
point, tap and it says on behalf of you
or the person that you're supporting.
We've got choose boards
around the classroom.
We've got visual aids to
communicate how we might be feeling.
Zoe: Also using visuals where possible
and thinking about my body language.
So if I am trying to get something
across with my facial expressions
or my gestures, I'd also try and
explain that to the child verbally.
Zoe T: By changing my communication style
from an imperative style of communication
to a declarative style of communication.
So that means that I'm taking the
pressure off the autistic person
by not making a demand on them.
I'm not issuing commands.
I'm not asking questions.
I'm making declarative statements and
enabling them to, and then pausing.
So make a declarative statement,
pause and wait, wait for that
autistic person to respond or not.
If they don't respond, then move
on or do something different.
But I would have been doing that
in the context of the relationship
that we have between each other.
Phil: You know, really
reduce the language.
And that's one thing that is easy to
forget, especially if you're working
with an individual who might present
as they understand what you're saying,
or, you know, might, you might be
able to converse or maybe even have a
good rapport with, but it's so easy to
forget that actually they might not be
processing what I'm saying, they might
just be giving a reaction that they
know is sort of socially acceptable.
You know, the social norm is expected.
Kerry: So yeah, we're trying to be
a communication total classroom.
So any form of communication, whether it's
grab the hand of the person, of the adult,
and take them to the thing that you want,
or whether it's a full sentence supported
by the visuals in PECS of "I want".